[Music]
I'm really looking forward to this
conversation just thought I'd give a
little bit of background and maybe play
a little clip from an interview I think
we did Jonathan over a year ago now
where we were talking about the initial
Jordan Peterson sam harris debate and
you made a really fascinating point
about the phenomenology of consciousness
and I think I talked to Jordan about it
very soon afterwards and we like the
seed was sown back then about maybe
having a dialogue around this this wider
topic of consciousness and maybe the
place that Jordan Peterson and Sam
Harris got stuck that could be the place
with its most fruitful to explore so
I'll just play that quick clip now if I
had a discussion with Sam Harris I would
just say okay look I know you don't like
religion I'm religious that's fine let's
not talk about that cuz gonna be a dead
end let's talk about consciousness let's
talk about that and let's lay it out
okay what does a world in which
consciousness is central how does it lay
itself out how does attention lay itself
out right it lays itself out in terms of
hierarchies terms of hierarchies you
have a point of attention and then
around that point lay the world kind of
flows out into chaos which is on the
edge even in your visual frame that's
how it works right so you have points of
attention and then on the edges you have
this chaotic space which is which is
kind of gray and not totally there and
so you say okay so now let's take that
experience of consciousness and let's
say that that's the foundation of
reality that's what he says he says
that's the foundation of reality well is
there an analog to that in a community
what does that look like what does a
commute what does the analog of
consciousness in a community look like
it looks like it looks like gathering
together around a point
looks like turning around appointed it's
it's circumambulation it's a it's a it's
it's a hierarchy of social of structure
and it ends up looking like a religious
ritual that's what it looks like right
because that's that's religious rituals
are have the same structure as the
structure of consciousness so I think
that that and then how does what does
that look like in time what does the
experience of consciousness to look
like if you see it with the frame of
time and what it looks like is a story
do you guys feel this like that that
point the phenomenology of consciousness
like what the consciousness looks like a
story is that
mase that could unstick this
conversation or how do you want to take
the what I mean not to be
instantaneously hyper meta but the very
first thing that happens is the fact
that we're even conscious of the fact
that we're talking about epistemology as
a thing I think that's already a piece
of bone sticking the conversation is
actually having awareness of the
underlying basis that gives rise to the
constructs that we happen to be
operating in and just being willing to
go down that stack as far as need to go
so so that we don't get stuck on things
that at least now in the contemporary
world we didn't used to have in
principle the capacity to have some
facility with so that was my the thing
that got that I actually felt stalked by
almost like choking on a bone when
listening to that conversation between
Jordan and Sam was the fact of kind of a
system illogical is just zooming past
each other right and the inability to
look at and say oh wait a minute we're
actually instantiating orthogonal
epistemologies and there's no there's no
basis to actually establish one as being
the dominant epistemology so that's it
we're sort of done there's no not off
you can see like what do you do in that
context that's kind of interesting
conversation what didn't doing her in
that situation and exploring it but it
felt like there there wasn't actually
the ability kind of step one level
higher or deeper Tiffany in your
preferred metaphor and have that
conversation one of the things that in
terms of sam harris we're going to start
with that conversation that i find
fascinating is that to certain extent
jordan Peterson talks about
consciousness talks about the
phenomenology of consciousness quite a
bit and Sam talks about it as well in
terms of in terms of the basis of the
world that is he really has this
meditative practice he has this
connection to Eastern practices and so
he has had mystical
it seems at least it's what he said he's
he seems to say that he has had some
mystical experiences where he's
experienced his the bareness of his
consciousness as this point kind of this
point of origin out of which the world
kind of lays itself out or comes comes
towards we could say and so what
fascinates me is that he has that
experience he has that understanding
let's say of the basic of the basis of
all our experience of being this first
person looking around and experiencing
the world but he then jumps from that
point to science and so he says here's
the basis of existence that is this is
the only thing almost that we can say is
real and then he goes from there to this
analytic mode which is that which is
actually an alienated mode where you
have to make the effort of alienating
yourself from your first-person
perspective and looking at the world in
this flat way whereas if to meet you
with five finest ranges that you if he
was able to understand how taking that
point of consciousness as the origin if
you follow the steps and then you
understand that these consciousness is
let's say come together and stack up and
that's how you build families that's how
you build larger units or you know that
you build these distributed
consciousness is whatever you want to
call it you know cities countries
identities that are larger than person
and that the way that within yourself
you function the way you have parts and
that those parts interact is the same as
how that happens at higher scale and
that that's the same thing that happens
in a story that's how we create images
all of these human all of the basis of
human culture and human wisdom is there
and religion is part of it so if you
look at religious practice you would see
that procession processing having sacred
spaces where everybody gathers together
and acts in the same manner speaks the
same words or sometimes it can be a
rhythm in that speaking there can be a
back and forth between two sides and
there can be a processing all of these
actions make a lot more sense if you
standing through the phenomenology of
consciousness but if you then jump to an
analytic mode where you analyze
everything flat in terms of its atoms
and its molecules and everything then
you look at the phenomena of religion
and you think it's it's idiotic because
it doesn't fit it doesn't fit that way
it fits through the through that other
side so I don't understand how he's not
able to like there's a weird blindness
in his in his approach to reality where
he jumps from one to the other
and he doesn't he's not able to make the
it's not able to draw the line in order
to to get there I don't understand to
interject here before you start Jordan
just because I'm what I'm hearing when
Jonathan says that and I'd not thought
about this before is coherence like what
he's talking about like speaking the
same words in a ritual together is feels
like coat like coherence being primary
in terms of consciousness and then a
shared experience of consciousness being
somehow primary which just I'm just
throwing that in because that relates to
something we've been talking about quite
a bit right I get the I get the feeling
like that would be in like bring that up
later I feel like - like feeling it now
sitting it now is great and it can
percolate I think it's actually gonna be
a moment I'm gonna I'm gonna do this
watch you ready 37 minutes from now
where it'll actually be alright so the
thing that I was noticing that was
actually kind of peeking my curiosity
and felt like maybe most helpful most
useful is actually should inquire into
into that that notion of how is that
happening because it's it raises the
question the bait the general question
is how does how does the the mode or the
way that a given mind and by the way I'm
making a distinction here mine the way a
given mind grasps or approaches the
questions that that arise for it
so in this case where we're talking
about sam harris or at least the
particular caricature of sam harris that
we're playing with the sandbox and
harris the will we now be poking at as
having this interesting certainly from
our perspective and by the way I share
this perspective
odd - characteristic of starting at
first person but then as soon as
thinking begins it immediately flips to
an obligate third-person perspective and
i recomment specifically obligate third
person which is to say without a
conscious choice like it's a it's an
unconscious almost like a structural
characteristic that forces the entire
awareness capacity the ability to
perceive what is real into that obligate
point of view such that it even because
of that the ability to actually be aware
of or notice the the curiousness the
almost to the feeling I have a feeling
of like the disorienting feeling of
moving from first person to third person
without any step in between so there's a
bunch of stuff there right is about the
notion of like the distinct which in
consciousness in mind the notion of what
mind is and how it actually emerges how
one might go about having this notion of
having an obligate perspective and how
that would happen and why it might
happen and even possibly thinking about
it in terms of given where we are now
like who we are as humans in the world
the cultures that we're in and the
things that we're facing is there a way
for us to actually be conscious of how
we design mind so that the mind that we
are using to apprehend world is most
suitable to the world we find ourselves
in hmm when you say design mind I'm not
sure what you mean you mean by design
your own mind or design people's mind or
design in artificial intelligence what
do you mean by design mind well
interesting I did not think about the
third but that definitely comes up
doesn't it
I was initially thinking about the first
and then as you were you know bringing
me to into more inquiry the question of
parenting becomes almost immediate so
one might assume that most minds are
developmental they they are developed in
the process of the coming in to be
becoming of a person and so whether
we're being intentional about it or not
we are contributing meaningfully to the
mind that a given child that we happen
to be parenting has yeah so I feel like
the first and first and second feel very
nice to me the third frankly is a little
bit scary for me and I'm kind of like
that far
well in terms of in terms of a child I
think that the the how can I say it it's
the best way to train a mind I would say
is loved it it's sorry to use that word
everybody fine but the the idea of this
is this is related to what I'm talking
about in terms of the notion that
consciousness stacks up or that person
stacked come together in terms of
communion and so the the idea of that
communion is the way to train a mind
that being in a relationship with
someone that's the real way to train to
mind that by attending you know by
paying attention to something by you
know treating them treating something
feigning a child is important and and
when you do that then you have two sides
which will appear right away one is a
side which is to encourage what is what
is what encourages the communion and
then the other would be to discourage
you know a right and a left hand right
hand to bring closer and the left hand
to move away and that actually is
training the mind in how to how to
interact with the world that is when we
interact with the world we have those
same two tendencies which is the
tendency towards one and the tendency
towards many you know the perceiving the
the one and perceiving the many when
you're raising up a child that's what
you're constantly doing in terms of the
child you're you're you're constantly
showing the child what is what is
straight and what is crooked you could
say and the child will have to explore
what is crooked as well they'll have to
you know it's part of doing it but then
they'll also see the consequences of the
crooked and the consequences of the
straight all this and so to me that's
how you that's how you you train a mind
and it comes back to this idea that the
RIA the first reality of human people is
is people like we we the first thing we
care about is other minds other people
that's good we care about first I don't
that make sense well there's a couple of
things that come up I mean what I would
say is the part of my my preferred way
to be in dialogue is to make sense
together
so did agree to which there's a material
for sense-making in front of us I feel
called the step that like step in with
my I guess you're a sculptor right well
for whatever reason I had a metalworking
metaphor come to me so I've got a hammer
banging on the on the metal I apologize
if those two don't go to whether you can
gather well what cup popped in my head
was this really nice plan words which is
attending rather than pretending because
what I've noticed is that many parents
and I have meaningful experience in this
pretend to attend and that is really
problematic and this I think is a
characteristic of a particular kind of
mind so we now have an interesting
feedback loop which is that first
question how do you actually shift your
own mind so that a habit of pretending
is actually able to be replaced by an
actual lived attending which then gives
rise to the possibility of then that
relationship with your child that we've
identified as perhaps being the way to
help them develop their mind yeah now
and I think I think that's when you know
practice is like practicing attention
itself in in the in the Christian
mystical tradition you have this idea
that there's a tension and then there's
memory you always have to remember
remember yourself
the idea is remembering God and
remembering death you could say
remembering the two extremes and when
you do that then you
it's dip it's you don't get distracted
you're well we end up it happens anyways
but it's like if you're capable of
keeping attention and keeping memory in
the sense of remembering not remembering
the things in the past but remembering
the sense of staying connected to
staying connected to some three memory
yeah exactly so it's like you you're in
this state of attention in memory and
then you it's more difficult but it's
then you won't pretend or if you do yeah
it'll be malicious if you do it won't be
again won't it will be even worse see if
you if you if you pretend when you're
attending because it'll almost be
immoral because you you'll be doing it
out of yeah yes I would say be profane
yeah because when if you well usually
we're distracted that's why we pretend
that's why we don't attend to
children because it's like we're there
with our children but we're thinking
about our job we think about whatever
other problem some stupid thing someone
said on Facebook or whatever and then
you know we're not there and and I think
but I do think that being there like
giving a child attention for like 10
minutes like actual real attention I
mean you can feed a child yeah that
child like actual real attention I've
noticed that if I can do that with my
kids like 10 minutes a day they're happy
then after that it's like everything
kinda is together but if I can just like
focus for 10 minutes then real real
attention then they know that that you
care and they know that they're part of
this family well here I flag violating
my own principal coherence there's
something there so just to kind of make
the the ding or the sound of the tone in
the in the the ether it was something
that there's a few things oh I was just
reading with my wife rereading Dan
Siegel's book on the whole brainchild
one of our we have a 11 month old mother
now yeah okay
and one of the commitments that we've
made we actually went through a program
called parenting a spiritual practice
twice that's produced by some some
Canadians and one of the things that
came out of that was an introduction of
Dance Eagles working with you know made
a commitment to reread that periodically
just to kind of keep the his good
heuristics don't you know his work but
they're very good concrete like here's
ways to deal with being in relationship
with the child's mind and one of the
distinctions he makes is between
implicit and explicit memory and I think
that was a there was an interesting it's
not a it's not a mapping I'm not
actually implying that's the thing that
you were saying between a kind of
remember there's like remembering things
that are in the past and I kind of
remember that was a coming together but
there's an interesting connection like a
like a tonal resonance between implicit
and explicit so explicit memory is what
you were talking about in terms of
remembering things in the past so
remember a few minutes ago when David
said that thing that's exclusive memory
and it's interesting to even feel what
it feels like to be in that mode of
explicit memory looks like that you know
the theatres of mine metaphor implicit
memory is the thing like you know how do
you ride a bike there's a process you
learned how to ride a bike and you built
it into your body you embodied the
capacity to ride a bike and I think
there's something very consonant between
that the two to embody the capacity to
live in continuity with life is I think
very close to what you're talking about
so yeah whoo the degree to which you
have been healthy you've actually become
whole in yourself so there's nothing in
you this between you and and the life
that you're in relationship with then to
be remembered would be to bring yourself
back to bring your implicit memory yeah
to tune your implicit memories so that
your implicit memory makes it not
possible for you to be present to the
moment fully
I think that in terms of tons of kids
you can see I can see it because we did
we homeschooled our kids and now my
daughter she decided to go to school
she's 12 and we're really nervous at
first because obviously a home school is
different you know just the whole
approach and it's more holistic it's
more about people and relationships you
know and giving the giving the kid time
to be really bored you know so that they
thinking about stuff and that you know
my son picked up the pianos cause he was
so bored and he started playing three
hours a day and we're like you know it
works but we were a little afraid of the
academic part because you know we didn't
hammer on that as much and so our
daughter went to school and she did
totally fine
like she's completely fine you know she
has she has she has good grades she
she's doing well and what I realized is
it has something to do with what you
were talking about in terms of I think
that what we gave her in homeschool was
not so much a bunch of stuff to learn
but rather a way of being and a way of
learning that that's so that's the
implicit parts like she knows how to
learn she knows how to be and so put her
in any circumstance
she'll be fine like she she might not
even if she doesn't know something she
knows how to to be quiet and to listen
and to catch the right pattern and then
to to to quickly catch up because she
can learn
and I was like oh okay so that I was
like okay now I know why we homeschool
you know like I understand what the the
advantage was it was really giving them
teaching them to your person first and
then you know after that you can slit
them loose and they'll do whatever
they'll be fine you know yeah yeah
there's a lot of cool things that like
branches that are popping off as the
conversation is opening up the one that
I think has the most it feels to me like
grit right now has the most relevance
was going back to the moment where the
parent is attending the child and the
way that the child has a relationship
with with another person in this case
that would me even in book with another
consciousness and then thinking about
because you actually made a very
specific reference and I'd like to to
bring it out to the or what's Eminem I'm
gonna do a twist so as inside so outside
or as outside so inside there the notion
of the the first thing the child is in
relationship with is their own interior
there's there the quality of the the way
that they themselves are showing up in
life of course as a child at the end
unit for newborn the distinction is not
a distinction so even the process of
actually being able to sense the
difference between what is them and what
is mom for example it is the first thing
and so in a very lived way one of the
very first practices that we were that
we practiced my wife and I with our
infant this came from the that program
that I mentioned was before we would
pick her up or before we would give
allow anyone else to hold her we would
just you know create a structure like
this your hands open and then give her
the time which has a I'm not a newborn
but within two or three weeks it
actually began to land to sense that
something was that there was a kind of a
possibility of relationship and this
gets to be held and then to signal
whether or not that possibility of
relationship was consented to because
it's a yes and the point there is to
actually create a feeling of in the
interior of the child the experience the
implicit experience but nothing
conscious
it's obvious that we're talking about a
one-month-old but the implicit like how
do I say this without a well that'll of
noise do a lot of clarity of signal of
what does it feel like in me when
there's a feeling of yes to something
and so I've noticed that that's actually
been part of a stack that there's been a
building at that that because she has an
ability to sense in herself when she is
would you say closer to or the you had
some terms like the many in this and the
single yeah one of the many and then the
straight and the crooked right yeah it's
actually in herself like okay so that's
a six that ah okay cool
it's that first person third person
distinction you know not that's crooked
that straight third person top-down
visual can you tell the pattern but
rather as you're looking at straight and
crooked are you always able to feel in
yourself what yourself is actually
telling you how to make that distinction
what's that distinction feel like in you
so that when you come across it in any
context now without having to do this
sort of weird semantic mapping you
actually will just look at and go oh
I've never experienced this before my
life but I'm pretty sure that's in the
direction of straightness yeah yeah and
you don't even think it it just happens
that's that's it that's why it's so it's
so interesting that I love so much of
what we are is just about being with
other people and it's just about and I
mean and I say that I'm on YouTube and
I'm talking and I'm explaining stuff to
people you know so it's I don't think
there's anything wrong with that but so
much of what we are is just this like
we're communal beings when we're meant
to be together and we learn from each
other and so you can kind of understand
the idea you know of a saint or of a
star at you know like a spiritual guide
or something this notion that even just
being in with someone who has attained a
certain more level or a certain
spiritual level that can transform you
they can it can change you just by being
in contact with somebody because a lot
of it is implicit it's like you're not
it's not so much it's not just the idea
of getting a teaching from somebody but
it is a it is somewhat how like an by me
they're being and so then once you kind
of get that you can understand why
people want to go to rock concerts why
people want to meet you know stars and
all this stuff it's it's a caricature in
a way it's not a caricature it's the
actual thing but it's it's a bit maybe a
little bit debased version of the desire
to be with holy people or to be with
someone who is manifesting something in
the world you know it's like the this
this person is there's there they're
just I mean I would say that I think
that seeing would have ended when
Peterson to me I saw something of that
where it was it was like because he
wasn't really sometimes he wasn't even
saying much like or he keeps repeating
the same things obviously you know I
mean I sure you've done a thousand shows
it's like you you're obviously repeating
you have to repeat yourself you can't
just be always saying new things and and
and then people just want to be there in
the room and be in the room where he's
saying the same thing that he said you
know ten times on his YouTube channel
and so it's like that's when you realize
just how much so much of knowledge and
so much of who we are is just about
that's why I use the word love because
it's it's about this actual connection
with somebody it's it's more than just
propositional oh nice you invoked it I
was that wondering like that
propositional down to participatory yak
that uh and by the way I'm just gonna
keep calling him Johnny because I hope
that it enters into the common
vernacular right
the journey be brought like I didn't
have that those concepts before I
watched his stuff and I feel like that's
just a really nice concrete but
fundamental way of just helping
understand that there's just such a
distinction yeah and and yeah I myself
have personally had the experience many
times just have been biting another
person and noticing by the way that you
know if you're in a particular moment
and you're having a conversation with
someone the thing that is happening at
the propositional level while it may or
may not be the intention like right now
like the conversation that we're having
explicitly at the propositional level is
almost certainly the least important
thing that's actually happening there's
a lot more going on and if and I've
noticed if I like watch the comments
by the obviously right everybody who's
watching something reading something or
participating in something is absorbing
the piece that is most imbibe Abul by
them its Forge they have the most thirst
and to which they have the most taste
yeah I've been watching the John verb
achy stuff quite a bit so maybe I would
liked it to think about some of the
things that he's talking about
especially if you just talked with them
I'm probably going to be doing more
discussion with him maybe an event even
here in Canada so it's something that
I've been thinking about quite a bit I
really appreciate the language that he's
giving in terms of and I think he really
understands a lot of the a lot of the
problem especially the problem of
progress I don't know if he sees it that
way but he understands the the the the
myth he doesn't understand it but he's
describing something which can help
people understand why progress is so
problematic because it's always like
you're gripping and then you're letting
go and so if you grip too tight then you
let go you have to create this optic
y'all that we call this optimal grip or
whatever and everything is like that
where there's this optimal grip but it's
always changing and it's not you always
have to kind of shift it in order to
move it and so you'll hear politicians
say things like you know we have to
centralize centralizing is the is
progress and then they'll centralized in
the centralized will exaggerate I mean
once they've centralized so much then
they see all the downsides of
centralization lack of particularity
lack of attention to to to particularly
problem they're like no no we need to
decentralized II centralized and
decentralized everything and so this
crit and then D centralizing is progress
right D centralizing his progress and
they don't understand that that the very
trade-off that you're it's always there
that trade-off like if you want the
medical system to be completely
centralized into one gigantic state-run
thing then yeah it's gonna be efficient
it's gonna do all that and then at some
point you're gonna run into all the
problems the particulars if you want to
be centralized it's going to be dealing
with everybody's local problems and it's
going to be great it's going to be super
expensive and then it's also going to
lack cohesive discussion between the
experts like you just can't avoid that
problem it's just and so that's the
that's
why hey that's one of the reason why why
progress is to me isn't illusions
especially like social or moral progress
it's always finding that optimal grip
there's a great quote by Rumi which I I
really find beautiful he talked about I
won't quote it directly he talks about
how if you keep your hand open or your
hand closed you know that's a paralysis
like you're paralyzed it's like you your
hand needs to slightly open and close
like the wings of a butterfly and that
is how you exist in the world it's like
this always this in breathing in
breathing out you know that's the rhythm
of existence you can't just breathe in
and think that you're on progressing
I've got more air and I've just keep
adding more hair more air and it's like
doesn't work that way you have to you
have to breathe out and I think that
that the language of this kind of
optimal grip stuff that he talks about I
find it's extremely useful for people to
understand know why complexity looks the
way does why efficiency isn't always the
answer you know that the idea that you
can make a robot that's more and more
efficient that somehow you think that
you're going to solve the problem it's
like no because as it becomes efficient
then you'll have the problem the other
problem which is the problem of all the
particular questions all the the
exceptions all these things that that
are real and that you have to deal with
yeah anyways that's the stuff I've been
thinking about just because I listen to
some of his podcast today and yesterday
so I was like well the thing to my mind
turned to there's a lot of things I was
noticing for example I'm not sure of any
of this I'm about to say is even vaguely
interesting useful but in any event it's
where we are as you were talking I was
noticing in in my in my mind different
frameworks that were kind of loading up
to potentially make sense so for example
as you were talking about centralized
and decentralized healthcare and I was
actually I was actually loading up a
paradigm in graph theory and network
theory that's actually able to do a
really good job making sense of that
particular thing it's almost like you
know as we're talking there's a sense of
like flipping through the toolkits
looking through the lenses or even maybe
the tones are the instruments like okay
where are we are where are we where are
we to be present to what's happening now
and I was just noticing like as I was
sitting there was actually noticing that
was building up inside of me and then
the thing that dropped was actually kind
of looping back to this question of our
of our sandbox of our this character who
has a has an obligate set of ways of
mine sort of a pretty progressive mind
and in the sense that you're using
meaning that there's a an over
efficiency and over over fit and over
optimization for a particular way of
being in relationship with the world and
in particular one that seems to have
actually lost this ability right so
there's two problems one problem is if
you're this all the time that's problem
one problem two is when you've actually
forgotten that you could ever do this
it's a so we can't use as a metaphor now
we have this funny thing where and we
have this moment we're in the very
beginning sandbox Sam has first-person
consciousness as the base and then
moment to sorry I move up one like from
zero to one it just goes like that it's
exact alright there's nothing in between
so calm so there's something about that
there's something about and we can even
say well this is sometimes obvious that
the exact kind of culture that generates
politicians who operate in this way
because there's a co-evolutionary
dynamic generates individuals who have
minds that operate in this way and
there's a lot of really good rich stuff
that if we wanted to we could
double-click on an explore both the
history of how we got here the
parameters of why we got here in the way
that we did and then of course the the
choice that we might what might it mean
for us to find a way out of where we are
which I would say is if it stopped like
the the kind of mind in the kind of
culture that shows up in this way has a
lot of stuckness because you know if it
turns out somebody's throwing a baseball
at you and having a hand that can't
close you're gonna have a very hard time
catching it yeah well one of the things
I think one of the problems I think that
got us stuck is I think
I think that we we have accepted the to
me we've accepted the revolutionary idea
like we've accepted that culture is
opposite let's say that true culture is
oppositional then you know the artist is
an oppositional figure that all culture
is there to oppose and you know the rock
rock-and-roll punk rock aesthetic all of
that is what we've accepted and so we
all understand the world I mean it's
it's not just it's not recent you know
it's Marxism it's it's even even before
Marx you know this idea of this kind of
radical dialectic we've accepted the
idea that the world works through
through through opposition and so
because of that what happens is people
will flip like people can actually flip
from one to the other they don't even
realize that they still are always
inhabiting this kind of oppositional is
kind of oppositional mode and and
especially and democracy is part of that
creates that issue too because you end
up you inevitably end up having two
parties and then you have it's in the
u.s. is like such a picture perfect
image it's like in this country just
split 50-50 right down the middle it's
almost like a like a you could it's
almost like a cosmic image where if you
set up two opposites well that's what's
gonna happen it's gonna sit up in the
middle and people are gonna take one
side if you're gonna take the other even
sometimes the size I don't even coherent
in in themselves like if you look at the
positions that all the Republicans hold
they're not actually totally coherent
and there and the Democrats are not
totally coherent but they just swallow
one side and the other and then it's
just it's just we have to you have to
fight with finally coherent is their
critique of the other side yeah you can
actually get it the story they tell
about the other side's weaknesses is the
most coherent part of their platform
yeah and so I mean it's a it's a it's a
very dangerous is definitely a very
dangerous way the ancient way was
dangerous too in a different way because
usually coherence would be on the inside
and the opposition will be on the
outside so you know you have you have
the Roman Empire and if you're Roman and
if you're if you're if you're an actual
Roman citizen you're right in the center
and if you're kind of periphery
peripheral to the Roman citizens then
your little further out and then yeah
you know then you have people that are a
little further out and then finally have
the barbarians that were fighting and
that we're trying to
fight off and so there's a coherence
shuts itself up in the hierarchy and the
opposition happens towards the outside
and so that has a very dangerous it has
a day in a dangerous aspect because you
end up dehumanizing those that are
outside but now with that with democracy
and a kind of dialectical thinking what
we've end up creating is the enemy
within it's so it's like inside your
thing you set up an opposition and so
then your enemy is your neighbor and so
man that is that is a it seems like
that's a dangerous place to stand
especially if it ramps up if it you know
if it stays at the low level just
discussion it's not a big deal but as
we're watching it ramp up yeah it's a
frightening to me I've seen some I've
seen some very good arguments I've seen
some very good arguments that it
inevitably ramps up yeah because as you
say it's almost like there's a the
paradigm that popped up for me to kind
of make sense of that initially was the
notion of a evolutionary landscape and
so there's like a niche a really
high-quality niche over here in left
space they're really high-quality needs
to be here in right space and there's a
niche construction where if I'm in right
space the more I moved to the right well
it's like a stable but stable place and
right space like I America is like
Eisenhower Republicans the the farther a
slightly farther right version of that
is ever so slightly more fit as long as
it's able to distance itself from that
which is further left and so there's a
built-in pressure to select for more and
more polarization yeah it just keeps
that middle which is really the actual
danger to the to the dyadic structure
what I was wondering was if there's a
way to imagine what else Wow I mean real
time right now guys it besides a king
David I mean I joke I joke but I think
that the idea of having characters or of
having characters that transcend the
political I think that that's the key so
I say a king or queen yeah it can be
that and it
has been in the past not that that's
problematic but it can be Saints - it
can be holy people that that are that
stand above the fray you know there was
a time for example in the US where
someone like Billy Graham for all the
criticism that I could you know I'm not
a particular fan of Billy Graham but
someone like Billy Graham actually stood
above politics and he would meet with
with presidents on both sides and he
represented a kind of father figure for
the nation and everybody could agree
that Billy Graham's a good guy you know
even if I don't agree with them and and
so it feels like the the current state
let's say and and maybe like in America
maybe one of the things that actually
played that role for a little while was
was kind of entertainment I think it's a
it's a it's once again it's a debase
version but uh you know you had these
let's say the talk show host of the the
Johnny Carson talk show host type where
he was speaking to everybody and
everybody could tune into Johnny Carson
and could watch on T Carson and there
was no politics there was no there was
no polarization in the in the talk show
it doesn't mean that people didn't have
their polarized views but it just wasn't
there and so now it's weird cuz now even
in entertainment things have polarized
really strongly in terms of mostly left
on the left but now we're seeing you
know with with uh with certain movements
like alternative media and comics gate
and all this stuff we're seeing this
this other side which is which is coming
about and his long is is getting it's a
it's getting bigger
yes sir my friend Zack Stein he because
met Zack at all
he's his his thing is education and meta
psychology which is I think very
consonant with Johnny B's vision of
fourth generation cognitive science and
as I understand it and one of the quotes
in his recent book actually has to to
precise with this notion that in the
states in the US as the the place the
locus and I was in the proper locus for
the cultivation of meaningfulness and
connectedness which is
say the family was most most meaningful
and then to the community the lived
community secondarily evaporated there
was a mapping or a grasping for that in
media and school which is a uniquely bad
place to locate that particular
developmental need and also having grown
up in America in that context and born
in 71 I mean I remember the time when
you would go to school and we would all
just talk about the TV show that we all
watched so there was a way to maintain
and it's almost like a Roman style
coherence as you say and there's a
notion of okay we're the in-group
because we all watch this show we can
all talk about the same almost like
mythopoetic structures we share we're
keeping up to space up to date on the
meta-narrative that is our our culture
our poor pitiful commercialized and
poorly written culture starring a David
Hasselhoff but nonetheless it's
something it's something coherent and
then as you end in both at a media level
because of the the deconstruction of
narrow broadcast channels you're moving
into cable an dimension into the
Internet and also at the level of the
sort of the continuous metabolism of
meaningfulness into acrimony it seems to
just be built into the heartbeat of the
Midway that particular structure of our
culture's design has also done masters
polarized so it's fragmented and then
polarized so even those things that are
not at all good for holding and
conveying meaningfulness are now also
absent which i think is a pretty good
finger to point in the direction of the
media crisis yeah and and the thing I'm
whether you said that I was Iowa I kind
of was reminded that one of the places
that the Romans tried to find that's a
togetherness was in their entertainment
so I mean the circus for all it's
horrible that's was a way a because also
it was violent entertainment just like
our entertainments violent was a way for
Romans two to be together right it would
to to to experience the same catharsis
at the same time and so it was you know
as the Romans became less
Eligius you know especially after after
Augustus and things started kind of to
fragment there at that at that time it
seems like the circus was a place for
them to to to come together but it's a
friend it's a fragile you know the idea
of finding yourself in entertainment
it's it's it can last a little while but
I don't think it's strong enough yeah I
like I like a mapping right now to a
good guy and often him carroll quigley
he was a historian in the mid century he
were a really good book called the
evolution of civilizations and one of
the things he talked about is that the
Golden Age is actually always the death
knell of a civilization that what has
happened is is that it's closed it's
optimized it's become progressive and
its vitality is being exchanged for its
for our hypertrophic ation of the things
that it identifies as success so it gets
a whole lot of you know this case gold
but it actually is losing vitality
losing meaningfulness losing
connectedness losing religion in the
deep sense and yeah I think that's
probably there's a map in there which is
to say that almost at the at the moment
if you have you shifted if the center of
the way that your society is maintaining
its integrity as a coherent culture is
living in the domain of media you were
already dead you may not you the body
may not hit the ground for a little
while that's for any how big you are and
what's going on but death has already
set in yeah no I totally agree and I
think that you know I mean I think that
it's interesting because we probably
wouldn't it would been difficult for us
to perceive it at the dawn of television
you know we wouldn't but now it's become
so obvious and we can see the trace we
can see the line from television to
Facebook and we can see it breaking down
and now it's like it's too late because
we're all on Facebook we're all on these
social medias we all when we see how how
how they're a caricature of
relationships and now how they're
alienating to our you know I keep saying
that Facebook is the ultimate version of
the star system that we created with
media and TV and movies and everything
where everybody is a mini star it's like
you that's what it is it's like you
you can have a little bit of stardom and
so you're not actually in relationship
with anybody you're just exposing
yourself and then everybody is watching
you
aha they're not at you and so they can
comment on your thing but they don't
have to they you can expose yourself
and so it's exposing and voyeurism and
it pretends to be actual community but
it's acting yeah it's just a little form
of stardom and so it's its front down to
the individual yeah but you can imagine
that that has the characteristic of
collapsing further and further until
you're not even attending to yourself
everything is performative you're
performing for yourself you're
performing for your friends and it's all
assimilation which another guy who have
just finally like grasped this guy named
baudrillard you have about like stages
or levels of simulation and how their
levels of simulation convert into each
other and again we can kind of look back
and say oh okay weird Stage four I can
see three two and one now because we've
got enough perspective on it but then
you get back to the fact that this nice
thing at least for the moment and I'm
kind of like remembering AI and once
again kind of shutting it behind we had
38 minutes yet yeah is the return like
the remembering that you talked about
earlier is that is in some sense
always available yeah even though we
found ourselves alienated in every
dimension
you know this the suburbs and the
television are part of the same
machinery like you walk around and by
the way where I live you walk down the
street and nobody out what are they
doing we're inside either watching TV or
staring at the phone and that's it so
the capacity for people to live in a
context where there's no human contact
is only facilitated by the fact that
they can get the scene you lack room
with human contact from media but
because they can get the senior actor of
human contact from media super salient
ly like okay Thor is a lot more
interesting than your neighbor yes then
you don't go outside and so you get this
positive for self reinforcing
destructive cycle but remembering is
always available and yeah
I sense a renaissance I mean this is
again you point to Jordan Peterson I
this is what I I identify as being the
most fundamental lesson of that event
yeah
the degree to which there was a
recognition on the part of a very large
number of people who were extremely
thirsty to imbibe something that was
real that there was something real and
maybe not for everyone and maybe not
completely real but real and for the
people who drank it it was a thing they
needed which kicks something off yeah I
I agree I I mean I agree I in the sense
that I've seen it myself I've seen
people you know I can see it in their
eyes you can see the change that they're
that they have this this like little
sparkle and so that's great that's
wonderful and it but it is it's varied
it's very difficult and that's maybe
that's one of the things that I struggle
with in terms of Jordan and in terms of
Bret and in terms of red wine sign and
all these people is that maybe that's
why also I'm the explicit Christian in
this whole thing is that I think I don't
see how his things that how this stacks
up you know and I'm really struggling to
see how it stacks up because one of the
things that let's say Jordan talks about
is the individual and I understand he
says and he doesn't do it in a kind of
individualist sense he talked about
taking responsibility you know
big response really for for things and
being an active agent in the world
fixing the things around your community
and everything and but it has to it
still has to stack up it has to stack up
to a higher degree it's like if you do
that let's say you you fix your family
and you do that then there those
families also have to come together and
then those families have to come
together there has to be it has to has
to go up higher it has to come together
in a higher sense and so that's why I'm
always invoking I try to invoke let's
say the medieval village as an image of
of an actual village of an actual town
which has a a hierarchy in the very
architecture of the town where you have
the highest point of the town is the
church steeple it's usually at the
center of the town the town gets built
around this church that's the place
that's our that's it like that's the
highest point that's what we all look
towards we know that that's what binds
us together and
we go there to be bound to to experience
a common identity and then we go back
into our homes and we reproduce that
identity in our families and then we
reproduce that in ourselves now I'm
going to talk down I know everybody's
trying to go bottom up that's fine I'm
not a problem with a bottom up but but I
also think it's important to some to
describe it coming top to top down so
and I think that so that would that ends
up looking like to a certain extent is
identity you can't get away from it and
so the desire to so it's like how do how
can we deal with that how can we deal
with the reality of identities as this
stacks up and not ignore it but then
also not create the danger of the
extreme that's a rigid identity that we
saw in in 20th century nationalism and
so but there but there has to be it has
to stack up towards identities you can't
you can't just be a bunch of individuals
and then have what the state like have
just this anonymous with it post
national state country like Justin
Trudeau sad about Canada so the Canada
what do you mean when you say identity
well well one like you I mean it can be
a lot like really like clans like
exactly like religious identity is like
saying I'm a Christian saying I'm a
Canadian saying I'm a french-canadian
that I share a common history and come
in with you know a common identity with
other people all these identities they
they they they and they are inevitable
in in how the world stacks up and so I
feel like no one at least like in this
IDW group everybody wants to avoid
identity because they're saying you know
inheriting the sovereignty of the
individual everything identities
dangerous identities dangerous it's like
you can't if it stacks up you can't
avoid it so we need to find a balance we
need to talk about how we can find a way
to balance these identities without
because that's what let's say like
that's the big crib it is biggest
criticism coming from the extreme right
for people like Jordan Peterson they're
saying you're ignoring identity you're
pretending like it doesn't exist
when it obviously it's going to exist
it's going to to happen but then they go
way too far and they're like okay so now
we're gonna be what is it like right you
know it's like the white race and all
this all these to me that's a bogus
identity but there are real identities
in terms of cultural identities and yeah
all that so here I thinking in the word
coherence probably as a the way I would
describe the thing that replaces
identity that plays the role that I
think is what you're talking about
and by the way has particular that
characteristic of top-down so it's we
might call the what is it that enables
things at the bottom to actually come
together into things that have and I
have an identity meaning a
meaningfulness as a unit a beingness as
as such that is real like actually
effective in world and ma'am it could be
very concrete it's like if one of them
gets old and infirm the others stick
around and support them like that's
that's what it means for that to be a
real thing yeah and then for that to
also be able to come together in in in
higher and higher levels of wealth
frankly just scale as you said you know
the the the the small family the
distributed family the village the you
know we might call the the bio region
whatever it is right some structural
element that has a vastus and all the
way ultimately to the to the whole thing
like the whole the whole world which I
think may or may not have been clear in
the in the video that you watch that I
talked about but that's one of the
things that I spend a lot of time trying
to point out is that that's where we are
like where we're at a moment where it's
no longer really an option of do we
learn how to actually live peaceably
with all of our neighbors because our
capacity to destroy things has become
it's just getting larger and larger and
larger every day and so what was a
beautiful proposition 2,000 years ago is
now simply what has to happen this is
just very practical so the vivid the
image that came to my mind collage she
had to one was I'm going back to the
Year image of the hand opening and
closing right so one of the problems
with identity is when it does that
and it's an obligate and and then
forgotten well I am NOT Roman but
there's something about Romanist that is
helpful in me being able to have a way
of being in relationship with the people
around me if I if I somehow what's a
term not defer but almost like the
fundamental sovereignty of the
singularity of my soul is connected to
the divine if I give that into something
which is intact less than that then I am
actually engaging in a profane act so
that I can't do that that is in terms of
the constant language of identity it's
it's doing this and then forgetting that
you could ever close your hand so to
become the identity become a
revolutionary French member to become an
Irish Republican or to become a one from
Texas to become a Texan as opposed to
being with in fact what you really are
which is vastly greater than any of
those things for be and yet also being
able to use those as we've being in
relationship so that's one side so then
the other side is okay would it mean
what does it mean to actually be able to
identify this is almost for me I'm
saying what's designed it let's think
about what are the design
characteristics of the thing that you're
talking about well to me to think that
I'm talking about it looks like I mean
it does it looks like a medieval village
is what it looks like the structure of
it that's what it looks like to me is
that there's something there's a
transcendent center there's a center
which is actually not of this world it's
not yeah it's it's beyond everything it
ended and that that's where we actually
meet it's not there you know it's
there's signs around it there's a church
and there's a holy there's an altar and
there's a cup and in the cup there's
there's there's wine and there's bread
but it's not there it's all it's it's
the night it's the seed in the seed and
the seed and seed it's like it's hidden
it's a hidden reality it's the you know
it's yeah it's the the pattern hidden in
the in the world so that's what is
transcendent and like you said that
reaches from there all the way down to
me in being created in the image of God
and so it's like that's the line and
then along that line then we have
communion communions of love that will
manifest themselves and so you'll have
and and those will be hierarchical and
in a proper sense in the sense that
there are those that are
and their their their responsibility is
to care for those that are below and
those that are below are there to
provide you know that which comes from
below provide food provide whatever is
needed for the the thing that's above to
be able to care for you and so it's like
just we can I say support because it
creates a nice symmetry there you go
somewhere and you get support and here
you go that's a that's a better word
yeah it's a good word and so to me
that's what that's what it that's what
it looks like that's the to me that
seems to be the only possible structure
for that to to happen like you need
something you need a tree invisible
transcendent in the center or else it
doesn't it doesn't or else it stops and
the relative becomes nationalism becomes
this and that it becomes you know even
in terms of religion like if we don't
understand that it's a mystery you don't
understand that
let's say that God transcends all all
transcends everything transcends even
our religious you know even the
religious frame that we have then that's
also a danger because then we have then
we have you know the Crusades we have
religious wars or whatever yeah but if
we but if we can fully see that beyond
even even though let's say the
revelation that we have or the church
building the tradition we have is true
that beyond that God is always beyond
God is always beyond beyond beyond is
not cannot be contained cannot be cannot
be framed
he's yarn so to me that's the only way
for it to to actually work I don't see
another way but maybe maybe it's just
because I mean maybe that that you can
understand by my whole story by why I am
Who I am why I'm doing what I'm doing
it's like obviously I've taken that I
drank that kool-aid and so now I my life
lays itself out that way well I
fortunately for this conversation I
don't I didn't drink that kool-aid and
you know I agree so that's nice I came
through this to this place through a
very different Road and it's a road that
it looked a lot more like Sam Harris to
be put right so I I can have a
first-person experience that what it is
to have it all look at third-person mind
and one where my my metaphysics right
and I'm actually gonna use that to be
more foundational than ontology didn't
include
the transcendence in a meaningful way
meaning there was not a way of actually
grasping the meaning of transcendence as
an aspect of the whole thing mechanics
you say reality or world it's actually
bigger than that and that's the whole
point and so in this conversation we've
actually noticed now three things so if
I think about and I think this is I
think I think there's a very precise
piece here it's not quite right it's a
little bit so we have our sandbox Sam
over here who is kind of representing
the aspect of the whole thing that we
might call science like I actually I
wrote it I wrote an article that
actually had this in it not Sam in it
but these distinctions so we might call
science knowing semantics propositional
knowledge models of reality those kinds
of things what's your part like they're
definitely a part and these are those
are the frames like you're talking about
frames creating frames put any things in
frames is very useful and it's a part of
the thing then we have and I hear I'm
kind of just forcing the fit but it's
not terrible it's we now have I can't do
sandbox Jordan we can do jumping Jordan
no that's just too hilarious sorry
sandbox Jordan who's kind of
representing living living this like the
actual like you said like take
responsibility for yourself take
responsibility for your family live it
in life does it does actually allow and
support you and thriving then it's a
good choice probably that whole story
and those are not the same there's a
distinct and I'm actually by the way and
this is gonna be a little bit
challenging but I'm map in my own
language so this is just semantics so at
this point I actually mapped with the
thing that Jordan Pederson is doing it
as religion as distinct from science and
then the third that you're calling out
which I do imagine does seem to me right
as missing at least explicitly and I
have the previous to sandbox people it's
the transcendent which is analogous
Tagus mystery and one can one can
include mystery in religion but I
maintain it's important to hold them
separately because they are in fact
different at least that category the
notion of the living 'no sand the
rituals and the use of the procession
and all the the things that we do that
enable us to be bound in real bodies
living with each other and then that
feeling and the sense of connectedness
to the transcendent all the way up and
down in these different levels is a
different quality and you have so those
are three different things and one of
the things that I've noticed in most
conversations is that most conversations
either don't have all three of those
things quite often they lack one or two
of them or the phrase that I used in my
article is they cross the streams
invoking remember our last vestige of
culture pop culture go special so
science doing religion a religion doing
science or mystery doing science or
mystery doing religion you think if you
just can hold it and say okay the the
transcendent is is you know it's part of
the part of the thing you have to have
the transcendent if you want to do what
we're trying to do so when you say I'm
curious about when you say that you said
the transcendent isn't part of your
metaphysics and so then maybe maybe it's
also know that I'm saying the
transcendent is part of my medical oh it
is sorry I thought you said what it
sounds like what I noticed is that it's
often absent from the conversation yeah
exactly yeah no and alternatively to
present and other things are absent
which is equally problematic yeah but
also because people often they don't
they I feel like a lot of people
especially the modern Christians they
have this weird two world view of
reality you know it's like there's God
in heaven and there's there's things
here and somehow separate like I don't
I'm Way more of a platanus like I'm
whoever playing this in the sense that
you know the transcendent happens at all
levels and things transcended all levels
if they're in the in holding a cup the
identity of the cup is not in the cup
you can't find it it's if you try it if
you accumulate the parts of the cup
you'll never get to the identity of the
cup the identity cup necessarily
transcends the cup and that's true of a
family is true of a country it's true of
everything and so it's like if you just
keep couldn't if you keep doing that at
some point it's like you just keep
having things which transcend the
accumulation of predict
it seems like transcendence is just a
part of a reality people call it
emergence because they don't like the
word transcendence but like I said you
can see it bottom up if you want but you
can also see it top down to me those two
are the same it's just a different just
you just stand in different ways and
just stand in different places to look
at it I by the way I'd added the middle
as well so you can bottom-up top-down
and right in the middle oh very cool bye
st. Maximus the Confessor who was a
mystic he talks about how he talked
about the mystic who perceives the
identities of things and their
particular separate so he can see the
spiritual essences and you can see the
particulars of something you know you
can see them both and then he realizes
that they actually don't contradict each
other at all that they actually are
there together that they they represent
the same reality that it's not that's
the that is really the Incarnation 'el
way of thinking that's to me that the
highest Christian understanding of the
world is is that you know it's platonic
in the sense that it believes in the
reality of essences but it's not
platonic in the sense that it also
believes that those essences have to be
incarnated they have to have body and so
it's like it's the meeting of the two
that middle that you talk about
that's where reality happens it's in
where the where the essences and the and
the particulars meet that's where the
one of the many where it meets that's it
that's the world That's Life that's life
yeah yeah in fact when I was earlier
struggling with trying to not use the
word real I would say where they meet is
what is real yeah yeah I agree
totally yeah I was just gonna interject
I mean we're getting towards probably
about an hour or so now yep but I just
want to ask one question if you've got
like a couple of minutes more sure and
what I was hearing you say Jonathan
about we need to rescue a sense of the
transcendent we I know we've talked
before about the need for either in a
place where religion we need something
in the place where religion used to be
or we need I mean I guess you would you
would probably say that we've got one we
need to renew jokes
that's why go ahead and also I heard you
say Jordan that you didn't what I heard
he say was he didn't grow up with a
place for the transcendent or that
wasn't part of your metaphysics but
you've learned that that needs to be
there needs to be a place for the
transcendent I'd love to hear where
where you might come together what what
needs to be in that space where religion
used to be or how do we renew that sense
of the transfer well the first there's a
bunch of things that come up for me so
the first thing that I notice is like I
guess care or carefulness or the fact
it's funny so even as a word the word
sacred is about to leave my mouth I
immediately want to warn be careful
because the world that we live in
doesn't have a clue what that means more
or less a lot of this has to do with
this obligate third-person we've been
talking about so or a lack of
carefulness with the recognition that
the very notion of the transcendent
can't be held in the words are using to
describe it it doesn't matter what frame
you're using it wasn't other where
you're drawing it or speaking it or
dancing it it doesn't matter whatever it
is is that best assemble pointing
towards that which it is certainly not
right and so to be able to recover or to
perhaps remember a capacity and a
facility the capacity and the facility
for actually being in relationship with
the transcendent is a real thing all
right so this is a key you can't try to
force March tool kits that were used for
creating models of reality into doing
the work of the transcendent they're
gonna it's not gonna work they're gonna
be like what the hell's going on or
doesn't make any sense because it
doesn't make sense in the context of
toolkits for using making models of
reality and semantic structures but it's
just that's not the thing but it isn't
to say that there isn't a thing there is
a thing we just have to actually relearn
or remember how to do it and some of the
places we were talking about like this
difference between pretending and
attending in relationship with your
child is a really good place to learn
that thing and to make it very grounded
right because we other thing is we have
we have this again like because of the
mistake of the way that we've embodied
the trend Center when we try to point
ourselves at it is we have a sense of
the transcendent as being somehow too
big
it's it's it can't possibly be present
to the moment of my relationship with my
child because it's actually this
vastness that is you know bigger than
mountains when in fact the reality is is
that it has to be present in every
moment in every experience in every
relationship and so learning and when
being relationship within it that level
is a great way of grounding it like oh
oh okay it's actually not crazy talk
it's not fantasy it's actually as real
as the particulars right it's the
particulars and the transcendent come
together into what is real and so
rebuilding a facility and a capacity to
speak about it or at least a point in
orient our actions and choices in
relationship with it is a tricky
business it has to be done with a lot of
care yeah no I I think I agree with
everything you said but of course then I
then I'll add my little thing which is
you know I talked a little bit before
about the problem the modern world has
in terms of oppositional thinking that
means that we've set our reality in
terms of opposition and I think that
once I realize that or once I realize
that one of the problems is this
oppositional attitude and so once I once
I kind of got that I realized okay so I
don't I don't need to see my place in
history as oppositional I don't need to
see myself as having to get rid of that
which is before rather I need to shine
as much light as I can on that which was
before make it bright making make it
alive and so to me the the solution
because we are all from I mean we all
share a similar history all the people
here that are talking we're all European
descent were all you know we are a
ancestors were all we're all at least
our ancestors were all Christians
probably not that far behind and so you
know maybe one generation maybe maximum
two generations behind and so to me that
the the solution is is to reconnect or
to Rico here to remember all of these
things is what I want and I don't want
and I want to - like I said make that
which we had as bright as possible so
that it so that it
alive today so that it can carry us so
that it can it can give us a sense of
place a sense of place in the continuity
of time and place in space and a place
in terms of our communities and I know
it's not easy because the fragmentation
is so strong in our community but I
don't in terms of the scaling up that I
talked about before that's the only
thing I see I see all the other types of
movements that kind of move yo religious
movements and these kind of pseudo
religious or kind of quasi religious
movements I see them as participating in
the in the breakdown in terms of the
higher maybe they can afford something
in terms of individual's own realization
but they they're participating in the
general breakdown so that's my you know
it's it's at all its its I know that
it's not it's a it's maybe idealistic
but that is that is at least the the
road that I've kind of got got myself on
well the last thing that came up for me
right there was it's kind of a it's very
much a double-edged sword and I think is
the way to actually convert it from a
sword into a plow sure so if you were
coming from the late 20th century what's
called secular humanists
scientific materialists lineage and you
would like the world to hang together we
have a very practical problem which is
that there's about a hundred million of
you and there's about seven billion
people who are deeply committed to some
lineage of tradition that it gave rise
to where they are today and the
likelihood that you are going to convert
them on mass to your particular
momentary piece of history is not going
to happen
zero is in fact zero so something has to
happen that action is able to do what
you're talking about to actually go the
opposite direction instead of trying to
to browbeat
the people who are holding these
lineages into submission actually cast
more light and shine more light with ms1
that's one edge because the other edge
is we have to figure out how these guys
are actually able to enter into a truly
non oppositional mindset and we need to
get our Protestants in our Catholics to
form forever like really forever stop
hacking at each other because of
disagreements about things that I don't
even understand and and and then expand
that out right because the big embrace
here is going to have to include there's
a there's a billion Muslims right and
they come with their own internal
conflicts with each other that's wrong
impermanent and then I've got a whole
lot of other folks with lots of
different lineages of greater size and
scope and antiquity and all of us are
going to have to be able to live
together really really well like at a
level of living together well that has
rarely been seen in a single household
much less than the entire human family
yeah yeah yeah that's you you just made
my hill a lot steeper there but now
you're on the right Hill that's right
yeah it's not the hill to die on me hmm
no in a beautiful image of a
double-edged sword being turned into a
plowshare or like that somebody
somewhere probably thought of that first
rebel wisdom is a new sense making
platform bringing together the most
rebellious and inspiring thinkers from
around the world if you're enjoying our
content then you can help us make more
by becoming a subscriber which will give
you access to a load of exclusive films
also you can then join our group zoom
calls to discuss the ideas and the films
and you can send us ideas for questions
for upcoming interviews we're also
looking for talented people to help us
out with editing graphics music that
kind of thing and if you're a regular
viewer you'll know we talked a lot about
the value of embodying or actually
living out the ideas that we talked
about so that's why we run regular
events in London check out the links on
the website for more and hope to see you
soon
you